"Just How Bad Is Hospital Food?"
Hospital food needs a revolution.
I was surprised to find out
that most inpatient meals
served in hospitals are not
required to meet any sort of
national nutrition standards
for a healthy diet.
And indeed, an analysis on
the nutritional value of food
served to patients in
teaching hospitals found that
many did not meet
dietary recommendations.
“Warning,” read the headline,
“Hospital food bad for health.”
A registered dietitian wrote
in to defend the hospitals
saying, hey, at least
over half the hospitals met
at least over half the guidelines.
And hey, they’re so stringent anyway.
Little eggs and dairy, and you
could blow through your limits.
“The provocative conclusions
of [their analysis] only lead
the media and the public
to conclude that we are
a bunch of dunces who
have no understanding
of the relation between nutrition
and disease prevention.”
Well, if the white coat fits…
Look, we spend a fortune
on training doctors;
you’d think we could
follow through on some
of the simplest things, like food.
“Good diet is as necessary
to recovery of health
as [anything else], and it is
folly to pretend that it is
beyond the power of our
profession to change this",
a line written 75 years ago
and still, there’s pushback.
“Perhaps, we should question
whether a ‘healthy diet’
given to a helpless patient
during a 2- to 10-day
hospital stay benefits anyone
or anything other than
the dietitian’s sense of ‘doing good’,”
responded one doctor, always bothered
when patients are deprived
of a desired morning egg
because a “healthy”
diet has been ordered.
I mean, what’s a few days of a little
heart-unfriendly diet
in the scheme of things?
But it’s the message we’re sending.
“The presence of foods
on the [hospital] tray
sends a message to patients
as to what is healthy
and acceptable for them to eat,”
responded the researchers
that did the hospital foods analysis.
“We still can think of no
better place or opportunity
to set an example of good nutrition
than when patients are in hospitals.”
After all, public schools
in California have banned
the sale of soda for over a decade.
Why not children’s hospitals?
In a study of California
healthcare facilities
serving children, three-quarters of foods
and drinks wouldn’t have
been allowed in schools.
We’re talking soda, candy.
Having unhealthy items
in healthcare facilities
and seeing staff consume
these products contradicts
the hypercritical nutrition
and health messages
children may get from
healthcare providers.
On adult menus, nearly all
meals contained excess salt,
with 100% of daily menus exceeding the
American Heart Association’s recommendation
for staying under
1500 mg of sodium a day.
This means meals offered to
patients may actually contribute
to the exacerbation
of the very conditions
that may have led them
to the hospitalization.
But if hospitals stuck to
the recommended limits of salt,
the food wouldn’t taste as good,
responded an executive
from the Salt Institute, to
which the researchers replied:
Taste as good? We’re talking
about hospital food—
it doesn’t taste good no matter
how much salt you put on it.
At the very least, we should
prepare all meals low sodium
and then, if they want to add
salt, it’s their choice.
If they want to get
someone to wheel them out
into the parking lot and smoke,
that’s their business,
but we shouldn’t be
blowing cigarette smoke
into people’s rooms three times a day
whether they want it or not.
Interestingly, studies
suggest that when individuals
are allowed to salt food
to taste, they rarely add
as much as often becomes
prepackaged within the food.
Check it out. Switch people
to a low sodium diet and sure,
they use their saltshakers
more, but overall,
their salt intake dips way down.
And the study subjects
said it tasted just as salty,
because salt added to
the surface of foods
makes it taste saltier.
But when a hospital meal
comes to you pre-salted
to the hilt, inpatients may not even have
the option to consume healthier levels.
In defense of their unhealthy food,
one hospital food service
provider explained that they’re
just giving people what they want.
Are we really going to deny
people who are going through
difficult times any small
comfort they can get?
That’s one of the reasons why
this clinical director sends
candy bars and ice cream
to cancer patients.
You know what else might
help take the edge off?
A nice long drag on a cigarette.
“Here you go Timmy, try this.”
Hospitals used to sell cigarettes,
primarily for "patient convenience."
“I don’t think I can deny
a paying patient the right
to smoke a cigarette,”
said one administrator,
“I will have to insist we
have cigarette machines
in the hospital, as a
service to the patient.”
But some made the radical
suggestion that tobacco products
should not be sold in the hospital.
This wasn’t from the
1950’s, but from the 1980’s.
Yet, the irony of hospitals
allowing the sale
of a major cause of preventable
illness and death in this country
had rarely been discussed
in the medical literature,
and it’s especially ironic
that smoking was, of course,
permitted in the doctors’ lounges.
To their credit, though,
U.S. hospitals underwent
the first industry-wide ban on smoking
in the workplace by the mid-90s.
Well, now “[h]ospitals
again have the opportunity
to take the lead and
create food environments
that are consistent with
their mission to cure
the sick and to promote health.
Through the simple act of
serving food that meets
national nutritional standards,
our hospitals will act
in the best health
interests of their patients,
and their staff, and will
undoubtedly again be leaders
in our ongoing dialogue on
how to improve the food supply,
which, in turn, will improve
the health of us all.”
Strict antismoking regulations
were often criticized
as being too harsh, as if
disease and premature death
brought on by smoking
were any easier.
Think my smoking-diet
parallel is hyperbole?
Well, guess what. Today, the
major cause of preventable illness
and death in this country
is no longer tobacco.
The leading cause of death in
America is now the American diet.
Hospitals in the United States
serve millions of patient meals
each day and are optimally
positioned to model a healthy diet.